Tom Paulin papers, 1972-2008
Emory University
Tom Paulin papers, 1969-2008
Paulin, Tom, 1949-
Manuscript Collection No. 880
51 linear ft. (86 boxes) and 8 oversized papers (OP)
Personal and literary papers of Irish poet Tom Paulin including correspondence, manuscripts, printed material, photographs, audio-visual materials, subject files, and materials relating to the Field Day Theatre Company.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 2001.
Restrictions on access
Special restrictions apply: Subseries 1.4 contains restricted correspondence. Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers. Letters of R.F. Foster are closed until 2041 (40 years).
Collection stored off-site. Researchers must contact MARBL in advance to access this collection.
Biographical Note
Tom Paulin was born in 1949 in Leeds but raised in Belfast. After attending Hull and Oxford Universities, he embarked on an academic career which began at Nottingham University; since 1994 he has been teaching at Hertford College, Oxford. Paulin has apportioned his literary life into two reasonably distinct areas: he is a poet, and he is a critic.
Paulin's first major volume of poetry, A State of Justice, was published by Faber and Faberin 1977; since then he has published The Strange Museum (1980), Liberty Tree (1983), Fivemiletown (1987), Selected Poems 1972-1990 (1993), Walking a Line (1994) and The Wind Dog (1999). He has received the Eric Gregory Award (1976), the Somerset Maugham Award (1978), and was joint winner of the Geoffrey Faber Memorial Prize (1982). In May 2000, he was awarded a three-year fellowship by the National Endowment for Science, Technology and the Arts (NESTA) in order for him to write a long poem "affirming the struggle and memory of the generation that fought the Second World War." The first part of this project, The Invasion Handbook, was published in 2002.
Tom Paulin's first critical book was Thomas Hardy: The Poetry of Perception (1975). After that monograph he turned to the essay form as his favored method of criticism, publishing critical articles particularly in The London Review of Books (LRB). Many of these essays have been collected together in two volumes: Ireland and the English Crisis (1984) and Minotaur: Poetry and the Nation State (1992). A further selection of his prose, Writing to the Moment: Selected Critical Essays 1980-1996, was published in 1996. More recently his critical work has been focussed on Unitarianism, the late eighteenth century, and particularly on William Hazlitt; in 1998 Faber published his The Day-Star of Liberty: William Hazlitt’s Radical Style.
In some ways, Hazlitt is a model for Tom Paulin's own mode of writing, particularly in Hazlitt's insistence on the blurring of criticism and journalism. Paulin's criticism tends to be in the form of the polemical essay, published initially in a general circulation periodical such as the LRB, and pitched at a reasonably general audience. As well as critical articles, he has written prose diaries for the LRB. But he is perhaps best known in Britain for his combative performances on "Late Review," a BBC2 television program which features intellectual disputation on various artistic productions.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of the papers of Irish poet and critic Tom Paulin from 1969-2008. The papers include correspondence; manuscript writings by Paulin including poems, translations, prose and criticism; manuscript writings of others; printed material by and about Paulin; photographs and audiovisual material; personal files and subject files. The collection also contains files relating to Paulin's involvement with the Field Day Theatre Company.
Arrangement Note
Organized into nine series: (1) Correspondence, (2) Works by Tom Paulin, (3) Field Day Theatre Company files, (4) Writings by others, (5) Printed material, (6) Photographs and audiovisual material, (7) Personal files, (8) Subject files, and (9) Unprocessed additions.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Barnes, Julian.; Chaudhuri, Amit, 1962-; Dawe, Gerald, 1952-; Deane, Seamus, 1940-; Eagleton, Terry, 1943-; Friel, Brian.; Heaney, Seamus, 1939-; Hammond, David, singer.; Hofmann, Michael, 1957 Aug. 25.; Hughes, Ted, 1930-1998.; Longley, Michael, 1939-; McGahern, John, 1934-; Monteith, Charles.; Morrison, Blake.; Motion, Andrew, 1952-; Muldoon, Paul.; O'Donoghue, Bernard.; Ormsby, Frank, 1947-; Sommer, Piotr, 1948-
Corporate Names
Field Day Theatre Company.
Uniform Titles
Late review.
Topical Terms
Critics--Ireland.; English literature--Irish authors--20th century.; English poetry--History and criticism.; English poetry--Irish authors--20th century.; Irish poetry--20th century.; Irish poetry--History and criticism.; Poets, Irish--20th century.; Publishers and publishing--Ireland.; Songs, Irish.; Theater--Ireland.; Theatrical companies--Ireland.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts.; Poems.; Scripts.; Sound recordings.; Video recordings.
Occupation
Literary critic.; Poet.
Related Materials in This Repository
Seamus Heaney papers, Michael Longley papers, Derek Mahon papers, James Simmons papers, Peter Fallon - Gallery Press collection, and Ted Hughes papers.
Description of Series
- Correspondence, 1972-2000, Series 1; Boxes 1-8a
  Scope and Content Note
  The series consists of correspondence to Tom Paulin from 1972-2000. The bulk of the correspondence is filed by individual correspondent. Many of the letters to Paulin engage with his poetic and critical life. Correspondents represented include: Julian Barnes, Amit Chaudhuri, Gerald Dawe, Seamus Deane, Douglas Dunn, Terry Eagleton, Brian Friel, David Hammond, Michael Hofmann, Ted Hughes, Michael Longley, John McGahern, Charles Monteith, Blake Morrison, Andrew Motion, Paul Muldoon, Bernard O'Donoghue, Frank Ormsby, and Piotr Sommer. Also included in the series is correspondence of a general nature, a small amount of correspondence by Tom Paulin, and restricted correspondence.
  It should be noted that we have also followed Paulin's practice of filing correspondence with particular projects on which he was working. This is particularly relevant for correspondence related to a particular work (Series 2), as well as correspondence connected to the Field Day Theatre Company (Series 3), the latter of which includes further substantial correspondence from Brian Friel, Seamus Deane, Stephen Rea and David Hammond. Materials attached to correspondence have been kept with the correspondence.
  Arrangement Note
  Organized into four subseries: (1.1) Alphabetical correspondence files, (1.2) General correspondence, (1.3) Correspondence by Tom Paulin, and (1.4) Restricted correspondence.
  Restrictions on access
  Special restrictions apply: Subseries 1.4 contains restricted correspondence. Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers. Letters of R.F. Foster are closed until 2041 (40 years).
  - Alphabetical correspondence files, 1972-1999, Subseries 1.1; Boxes 1-6
    Arranged in alphabetical order.
    - Adamson, Ian, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Amiran, Eyal, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Amis, Martin, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Annan, Lord, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Astley, Neil, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Baker, Kenneth, 1990-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bardon, Jonathan, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Barnes, Julian, 1989-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bateson, F. W., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bayley, John, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bednarowska, Dorothy, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Berlin, Isaiah, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Berry, James, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Boston, Richard, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Brady, Conor, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bragg, Melvyn, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Brighton, Pam, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bromwich, David, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Brown, Eric and Deirdre, 1979-1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Brown, Terence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bullock, Lord, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Burris, Sidney, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Buttress, Derrick, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Byatt, Antonia, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Calder, Angus, 1987-1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Cameron, Ken, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Carey, John, 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Chaillet, Ned, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Chaudhuri, Amit, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Chênetier, Marc, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Cole, Barry, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Conner, Lester, 1984-1992 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Conner, Noel, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Corcoran, Sean, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Craig, Pat, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Crick, Bernard, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Croft, Andy, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Cronin, John, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Crotty, Patrick, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Crowley, John, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Crowley, Tony, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Crozier, Eric, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Cullingford, Elizabeth Butler, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Cutts, Anna, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Czerniawski, Adam, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Davids, Roy, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Dawe, Gerald, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Deane, Seamus, 1981-1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Delaney, Frank, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - De Souza, Eunice, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Dewar, Alan, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Dobson, Ralph, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Dodds, E. R., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Dolan, Terry, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Donnellan, Declan, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Donaghue, Denis, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Dunn, Douglas, 1970-1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Eagleton, Terry, 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Easthope, Anthony, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Edwards, Ruth Dudley, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Elliott, Andrew, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Elliott, Marianne, 1982-1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Evans, Matthew, 1986-1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Fallon, Peter, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Fauchereau, Serge, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Fisher, Roy, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Fitzgerald, Garrett, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Fitz-Simon, Christopher, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Fletcher, Ian, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Flynn, Tony, 1980-1987 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Foot, Paul, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Foster, Jack, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Frazier, Adrian, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Friel, Brian, 1981-1999 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Garey, Gill, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Giese, Rachel, 1984-1993 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Gray, Nigel, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Greacen, Robert, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Greaves, Desmond, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Green, Arthur, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Grene, Nicholas, 1984-1997 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Griffiths, Trevor, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Gross, John, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Gross, Philip, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Haffenden, John, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Hamilton, Ian, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Hamilton, Paul, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Hammond, David, 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Hanley, Keith, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Healey, Denis, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Hirst, Mike, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Hitchens, Christopher, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Hofmann, Michael, 1987-1993 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Holland, Mary, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Holman, David, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Holstun, James, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Horovitz, Michael, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Hufstader, Jonathan, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Hughes, Eamonn, 1982-1987 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Hughes, Glyn, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Hughes, Ted, 1992-1998 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Hynes, Garry, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Hynes, Samuel, 1977-1997 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Jack, George, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - John, Bridget, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Johnstone, Dillon, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Johnstone, Robert, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Jones, Stanley, 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Joseph, Larry, 1995-1997 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Kearney, Richard, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Kerbrat, Patrice, 1974-1987 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Kiberd, Declan, 1985-1998 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Kilmartin, Terence, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - King, Peter, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Kinsley, James, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Kirkland, Richard, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Kureishi, Hanif, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Lee, Hermione, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Lindsay, Nick, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Logan, Bill, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Longley, Edna, 1978-1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Longley, Michael, 1978-1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Lonsdale, Roger, 1987-1999 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Lucas, John, 1984-1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - McCann, Peggy, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - McClelland, J. S. and Tina, 1978-1996 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - McCrum, Robert, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - McDonald, Marianne, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - McGahern, John, 1990-1995 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - McKendrick, Jamie, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Mahon, Derek, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Marcus, David, 1981-1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Marken, Ronald, 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Martin, Graham, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Mendelson, Edward, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Messent, Pete, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Middleton, Stanley, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Miller, Karl, 1981-1992 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Montague, John, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Monteith, Charles, 1976-1991 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Morrison, Blake, 1978-1993 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Morton, Neill, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Motion, Andrew, 1975-1999 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Muldoon, Paul, 1975-1999 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Murphy, Richard, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Nairn, Tom, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Neve, Michael, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Norbrook, David, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Nuttall, Tony, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - O'Brien, George, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - O'Connell, Kevin, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - O'Donoghue, Bernard, 1972-1999 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - O'Grady, Timothy, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - O'Hagan, Sean, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - O'Hanlon, Redmond, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Orbach, Susie, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Ormsby, Frank, 1973-1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Paisley, Ian Jr., 1994 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Pybus, Rodney, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Quinn, Gerard, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Raine, Craig, 1977-1991 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Rawson, Claude, 1983-1987 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Rea, Stephen, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Reid, Christopher, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Rice, Adrian, 1993-1999 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Ricks, Christopher, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Robinson, Eric, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Roche, Tony, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Ross, Alan, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Rowse, A. L., 1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Rushdie, Salman, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Ryle, John, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Said, Edward, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Sail, Lawrence, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Schmidt, Michael, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Seddon, Pete, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Slater, Ann Pasternak, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Sommer, Piotr, 1976-1986 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Stewart, A. T. Q., 1995 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Stoppard, Tom, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Sweetman, David, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Thompson, Molly, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Townshend, Pete, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Traynor, Shaun, 1985-1999 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Treglown, Jeremy, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Turville-Petre, Thorlac, 1983-1987 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Uglow, Jenny, 1989-1994 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Walsh, Louis, 1983-1987 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Williams, David, 1974-1985 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Williams, Jonathan, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Wills, Clair, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Wood, James, 1993-1997 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Wyndham, Francis, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - General correspondence, 1973-1999, Subseries 1.2; Boxes 7-8: folder 6
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - 1973-1979 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1982 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1984 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1987-1991 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 1997 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1998 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - January-April 1999 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - May-June 1999 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - July-October 1999 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence by Tom Paulin, 1982-2000, Subseries 1.3; Box 8: Folder 7
    - Correspondence by Tom Paulin, 1982-2000 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Restricted correspondence, 1980-1998, Subseries 1.4; Box 8a
    - Foster, R. F., 1980-1997 (Box 8a, Folder 1)
    - Heaney, Seamus, 1980-1998 (Box 8a, Folder 2)
- Works by Tom Paulin, 1971-1994, Series 2; Boxes 9-22
  This series contains the manuscripts, typescripts and printed material of Tom Paulin's own work. Highlights include the notebook series, which runs from 1971 to 1994 virtually uninterrupted. The notebooks include a range of material, from personal entries, to poetic drafts, to research notes. Also present are the manuscripts from virtually all of Paulin's major poetry collections, as well as drafts of much of his critical output and various scripts.
  Organized into six subseries: (2.1) Notebooks, (2.2) Poetry, (2.3) Prose, (2.4) Criticism, (2.5) Scripts, and (2.6) Works edited.
  - Notebooks, Subseries 2.1; Boxes 9-10
    - Notebook (small blue Cambridge), ca. 1971. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries and notes. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Notebooks (2; one small blue hardback, one small red paperback), ca. 1972. Both contain multiple poem drafts, diary entries and notes. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Notebook (small blue Challenge), ca. 1973. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries and notes. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Notebook (small black), ca. 1973-1974. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries and notes. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Notebook (small black Challenge), ca. 1974-1975. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries and notes. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Notebook (small black, with red spine), ca. 1975-77. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries and notes. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Notebook (large black, hardback Alwych), ca. 1977-1979. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries and notes. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Notebook (small black Alwych), ca. 1979-1980. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries and notes [many notes on Kant]. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Notebook (small black Alwych), ca. 1981-1984. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries [including year in America] and notes. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Notebook (large black), ca. 1984-1988. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries and notes. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Notebook (small black Alwych), ca. 1987-1992. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries [including trips to India, 1987 and 1990] and notes. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Notebook (small black Alwych), ca. 1992-1994. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries and notes. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Notebook (small black Alwych), ca. 1994-1997. Contains multiple poem drafts, diary entries and notes. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Notebook containing Romanticism notes [ca. 1993] (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Poetry, Subseries 2.2; Boxes 11-21, OP 1-2
    - A State of Justice (1977)
    - "A Desert Development" (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - "Practical Values" (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - A State of Justice, typescripts, some corrected (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - A State of Justice, typescript (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - A State of Justice, reader's typescript (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - A State of Justice, typescript with printer's annotations (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - A State of Justice, page proofs, corrected (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - A State of Justice, correspondence and associated materials (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - A State of Justice, reviews (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - The Strange Museum (1980)
    - "Anastasia McLaughlin" (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - "Anonymous Biography" (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - "Atlantic Changelings" (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - "An Authorised Fear" (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - "Before History" (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - "The Civil Lovers" (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - "Cross on a Circle" (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - "A Frame, an Anniversary" [variant title: "An Anniversary"] (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - "The Garden of Self-Delight" (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - "Going in the Rain" (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - "The Harbour in the Evening" [variant title: "Evening Harbour"] (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - "Hidden Face" (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - "The Idea in History" (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - "The Impossible Pictures" (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - "In the Egyptian Gardens" (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - "In the Lost Province" (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - "In the Meat-Safe" (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - "Line on the Grass" (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - "A Lyric Afterwards" (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - "Man with Hookah" (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - "The Noon of Bodies" (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - "The Other Voice" (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - "A Partial State" (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - "Personal Column" (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - "Pings on the Great Globe" (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - "Pot Burial" (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - "Purity" (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - "Second-Rate Republics" (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - "Song" (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - "Song for February" (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - "Still Century" (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - "The Strange Museum" (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - "Surveillances" (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - "Traces" (Box 12, Folder 34)
    - "Trotsky in Finland" (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - "What is Fixed to Happen" (Box 12, Folder 36)
    - "Where Art is a Midwife" (Box 12, Folder 37)
    - "Without Knowledge" (Box 12, Folder 38)
    - "Without Mercy" (Box 12, Folder 39)
    - The Strange Museum, notebooks [3] (Box 12, Folder 40)
    - The Strange Museum, printer's proof, annotated (Box 12, Folder 41)
    - The Strange Museum, miscellaneous (Box 12, Folder 42)
    - The Strange Museum, correspondence (Box 12, Folder 43)
    - The Strange Museum, reviews (Box 12, Folder 44)
    - Liberty Tree (1983)
    - "After the Summit" (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - "As a White Lodge in a Garden of Cucumbers" (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - "Black Bread" (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - "A Brackish New Year" [variant title: "New Year"] (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - "A Daily Beauty" (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - "Father of History" [variant title: "The Father of History"] (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - "Foot Patrol, Fermanagh" [variant title: "Foot Patrol in Fermanagh"] (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - "For the Kilogram of the Archives" (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - "L'Envie de Commencement" (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - "Local Histories" (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - "Martello" (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - "Of Difference Does it Make" [variant title: "The Wild Birds Act (1931)"] (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - "Politik" (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - "A Rum Cove, a Stout Cove" (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - "S/He" (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - "Signing the Treaty" [variant title: "Signing; Peace"] (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - "Under Creon" (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - "A Written Answer" [variant title: "An Exercise in Practical Criticism"] (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - "Yes, the Maternity Unit" (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Liberty Tree, set of typescripts [includes some poems not included in published edition] (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Liberty Tree, miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Liberty Tree, reviews (Box 13, Folder 22)